Ghislain Brault-Joubert

Analytics Leader & Actuary ghislain@ghbrj.ca | Montreal, QC | 514-726-0359

About Me

Analytics Leader and Actuary. 15+ years of experience in Insurance and the Analytics space. Everyday I strive for superior, impactful decision-making with data through my work and teams.

I help business leaders with useful data products & insights. I grow and lead analytics teams. I provide analytics leadership to influence business strategy, roadmaps and outcomes.

Experience

Sr. Manager¹, Claims Analytics

Co-operators General Insurance Co. | Montreal, QC

January 2020 — Present

Claims Business partners needing Data & Analytics solutions to drive better decision-making

Dealt with business problems ranging from *workforce management*, *process improvement* such as work segmentation & assignment, *quality assurance & risk control* and management of *vendor relationships and performance*

The business of settling claims is the promise made to \sim 950K policyholders when things get bad, paying out roughly \$2B per year. The claims workforce is \sim 1600 employees reporting to 8-10 Assistant Vice-Presidents (AVPs) having similar but typically competing needs. Tremendous opportunities to reduce costs in an environement where analytics maturity is lower but developing

Acted as *Product Owner*; Facilitated the elicitation of business problems & decisions with claims leaders where data & insights are useful; helped them define priorities and develop actionable plans; drafted business cases, influenced initiation and planning of foundational projects & products; supported execution and delivery of value by articulating needs to data & analytics delivery teams and validated end products

Skills: Problem Solving with Data | Strategic & Tactical Planning | Product Management | Persuasive Communication

Data & Analytics professionals needing strong leadership and a supportive environment to thrive

The need was to build and grow a team of analytics professionals, raise team/individual performance & engagement while ensuring the work of the team meets business needs and high quality standards

Critical because of a rapid and significant increase in demand and rising expectations from Claims partners for decision-making with data. While growing, it was important to ensure the professional and personal wellbeing of the group of $\sim 15\text{--}30$ team members

Acted as *people leader*, defined team mandates, roles & responsibilities and performance expectations; Hired 15+ data professionals; Evaluated & rewarded achievement of goals; Influenced & implemented restructures

Acted as *practice leader*, defined and negotiated operating and service models with Claims and other partners; Defined related workflows (intake, prioritization, execution) and implemented agile delivery principles; Built and implemented change management plans;

Acted as *technical supervisor*, provided support and coaching on technical matters; Accompanied team members in their career development

Skills: People Leadership | Performance Management | Recruitment | Negotiation | Change Management | Technical Supervision

Actuarial Manager² & Expert

Co-operators General Insurance Co. | Montreal, QC

May 2014 — January 2020

Driving profitable growth of commercial risks through pricing initiatives

Led all aspects of actuarial work for a portfolio of commercial risks worth ~\$300M in annual premium. Delivered rate indications, segmentation analyses and related system implementations. Designed and implemented new rating algorithms and a risk selection framework.

Supervising a team of actuaries

Oversaw the professional and personal wellbeing of about 6-8 team members, setting goals & evaluating performance. Acted as technical supervisor, providing support and coaching on technical matters; Accompanied team members in their career development

Actuarial Consultant

Intact Financial Corp. & AXA Canada | Vancouver, BC

August 2009 — April 2014

Led Commercial Lines pricing assignments in Western Canada. Business lines included commercial automobile rate filings, small businesses, mid-market commercial, large accounts, specialty lines (E&O, D&O) and earthquake coverage

Skills & Knowledge

Business Insurance | Property & Casualty Actuarial Practice | Agile Delivery

Technology Atlassian (Jira, Confluence, Bitbucket) | R | SQL | Virtual Whiteboards (Miro, Mural) | Guidewire Policy Center & Claim Center | Genesys

Professional Designation

Fellow, Casualty Actuarial Society (FCAS)

May 2012 — Present

Fellow, Canadian Institute of Actuaries (FCIA)

Expired | November 2012 — September 2022

Education

M.Sc. Microprogram - Business Intelligence Data mining

HEC Montreal | Montreal, QC

2018 - 2019

B.Sc. Actuarial Science

Laval University | Quebec City, QC

2004 - 2007

Volunteer and Other Experience

Member of the Board of Directors

Bibliothèque d'Outils La Remise | Montreal, QC

October 2017 — April 2019

Montreal's first tool library. Helped the cooperative consolidating and growing its service offering to the members of the local community.

Young Directors Program 2016-2017

Institute for governance of private and public organizations (IGOPP) | Montreal, QC

Nov 2016 — May 2017

More About Me

Core Values Curiosity | Humbleness | Authenticity | Courage | Continuous Learning

Top Strengths Ideation | Adaptability | Strategic | Individualization | Learner (From StrengthFinder 2.0)

Languages French (Native) | English (Full professional proficiency) | German (Elementary) | Spanish (Want to learn)

References available upon request

- 1. As Sr. Manager, I supervised managers and data analysts & scientists←
- 2. As Manager, I supervised actuaries (individual contributors, junior to senior) ←